the intellectual dark web was first
named by the mathematician and physicist
Eric Weinstein on Sam Harris's waking up
podcast in January 2018 it attempted to
join together an unlikely group of
intellectuals and alternative media
personalities all the way from
psychologist Jordan Peterson to
podcaster and martial arts commentator
Joe Rogan figures from across the
political spectrum but all supposedly
united by their willingness to have open
and difficult conversations the name
stuck interest in the phenomenon quickly
spread far and wide with many thousands
joining the conversation online welcomed
by some ridiculed by others and even
questioned by some in the group it's
like a herd of cats right because so I
thought about well what what what unites
us to the degree that there's an us
because that's not so self-evident
there's enough of an us so that the name
emerged and it's stuck so so there's
something in common because otherwise
the name wouldn't have stuck right you
can't name nothing it doesn't work so
what is the intellectual dark web people
in the group tend to reject orthodoxy
tend to reject ideology tend to be
interested in first principles thinking
meaning that if you you don't take
something on faith it's a very smart
concept to try to corral a very
difficult group of very disparate people
into one orbit I think everybody who's
being described as a member that I the
IDW probably has among other things one
thing in common which is they all are
used to being held at for saying things
that are self-evident how old that in
public only to then discover that the
public come up to them in private and
say thank you so much for saying what we
think I would say it is actually the
manifestation of the
process of thinking that's more
important than the conclusions that are
generated you need a group of people who
are willing to say hey you know you made
a better point I changed my mind and
I've learned something that I didn't
think about and that kind of integrity
in a conversation is what characterizes
a lot of the internal IDW discussion to
me it's that people agree not on their
positions they may not even agree as to
what the facts are but they usually
agree as to what constitutes
conversation the intellectual darkweb
seemed like something Eric Weinstein
came up with on the spur of the moment
but it wasn't it had been years in the
making part of me wants to work quietly
and part of me realizes that we have to
work in some public facing capacity and
I personally have found it much more
comfortable to have a private life to
not have everything that I'm thinking
broadcast to a large audience but I
think we've run out of time and so I
think some of us are somewhat
reluctantly choosing to make a different
call now I think that with the current
administration and the White House
you're seeing a real discontinuity with
the past and it wasn't the discontinuity
that I was hoping for we had to break
with the past and I think that the way
in which we are now breaking with the
past is so destructive nobody knows what
to believe nobody quite knows what's
true nobody knows where to turn this is
not a tenable situation and so either
we're going to descend into some kind of
permanent chaos or there is going to be
have to be something that we reboot from
and that thing cannot be simply left or
simply right and that's one of the
reasons the IDW is hopeful to me this is
the origin story of the IDW
[Music]
what started off this path that I find
myself on is that I was curious about
certain things curious about the world
and I wanted to ask a bunch of questions
about well really pretty much everything
and I find that if you keep asking why
questions you eventually either a get
tired or B become a theoretical
physicist or mathematician and so many
of the deepest questions led to a kind
of disciplined way of thinking about the
world where we see all of the complexity
in the world around us as being built up
from very simple and beautiful patterns
and I think was my desire to contribute
to that story in particular with
theoretical physics that began my path
but at the time that I really emerged as
an adult theoretical physics was in a
great deal of difficulty in trouble and
I think as I came to understand that
there was a big story that was going to
affect everything that I cared about it
was going to affect the markets it was
gonna affect our families our sense of
ourselves our security and that story is
the story of what happens when humans
get addicted to high levels of broadly
distributed stable technology let growth
and then are denied the ability to
continue on that path that means that
you're set up potentially for war for
civil unrest for communism if people try
to grab what their neighbor has or
fascism if people try to maintain order
at all costs I define this thing called
an ego or an embedded growth obligation
and an embedded growth obligation is how
fast the structure has to grow in order
to maintain its honest positions so if
you have a situation in which you have
trial lawyers and they're supported by
various associates and the associates
all want to become partners and trial
lawyers themselves then what you have is
you have a situation where the law firm
has to grow at a very fast clip if all
those people are going to be satisfied
with their job decisions well very
quickly that ability to grow runs out
and then people want to know why am i
stuck in a position going nowhere
well the same thing was happening in
theoretical physics is happening in
mathematics it was happening in the
pension funds it was happening
absolutely everywhere except for a small
number of places like startups and hedge
funds which were a period of time were
able to buck that trend and as I came to
understand that we were in some sort of
society-wide Ponzi scheme since the late
60s early 70s and that there was no way
to continue to grow our way out
using the previous tools I started to
understand that society was going to be
lying about almost everything at almost
all times and that's a very terrifying
thought to have we have effectively
entered a period in which we cannot
trust our experts and I think that what
began as a desire to contribute it to do
real work ended with an understanding
that we've got two generations of
institutional experts that are corrupted
and that we cannot wake up from this
crazy fever dream that we're all in
because we can't figure out who we can
still trust the doctors are compromised
the professors are compromised the
journalists are compromised the
politicians are compromised about the
only thing that isn't badly compromised
are people with an independent source of
sustenance individuals and very small
groups are about the only thing that is
free of this disease of the embedded
growth obligation and so the paradox is
is that the individuals have to save the
institutions that are trying to
extinguish them because the
institution's don't want to hear this
message but in fact if they don't make
use of the tiny number of people
functioning as individuals or in smaller
organizations all of this is going to
collapse because it cannot continue
along its current it X
path that exponential gave out a long
time ago and it's like wily coyote
running off of the cliff as soon as he
realizes that there's nothing holding
him up down we fall there's two games
here there's trying to get the best deck
chairs on the Titanic and there's trying
to rescue the ship
and in general nobody can think of how
to rescue the ship which is a daunting
task so instead what we're doing is
we're fighting for position in a losing
game and it's important that that stop
[Music]
you've you've talked about this phrase
the war on excellence that sounds like a
very counterintuitive or a very odd
thing to be declaring war on well yeah
so it has to do with excellence in and
of itself isn't the problem the problem
is that we don't realize that excellence
is a modality that is expensive when we
pursue excellence we usually pursue some
activity that has very low variance an
excellent sprinter is going to be
somebody who's times are usually very
tight around their personal best
well those low variance behaviors are at
the cost of high variance behaviors and
most of what I think actually ends up
moving the dial in human history is high
variance human activity so what is it
that allows somebody who's as unreliable
as Jim Watson of double-helix Fame to
repeatedly deliver outstanding
discoveries so you you have a guy who
you can't take to any party and on the
other hand a giant chunk of modern
molecular biology is due to him and
cellular biology so you have very high
variance individuals who are mad
they're difficult they're unpleasant
they're time-consuming but they're able
to play the far right tail of the
distribution and bring us unbelievable
wonders so a famous example for me is
Bill Shockley who was a eugenicist and
kind of a bit of a nutcase with respect
to certain ideas too many on the other
hand you know he was one of the prime
reasons that we got the semiconductor
and built an industry around it and if
you think about all of the things that
are done with transistors you know a lot
of them go back to Bill Shockley okay
well are we willing to give up our
semiconductors in order to protest
Shockley's excesses in the field of
eugenics I in general or not I'm willing
to tolerate a lot of eccentricity and
difficult behavior and unpleasant people
and I think it's absolutely imperative
that we realize that as a society we are
standing on the shoulders not only of
giants but of jerks of unseemly people
very marginal individuals who have
nevertheless contributed much of the
genius that undergirds our modern
productive society and I think it's
absolutely appalling that we don't even
know our own history to know this
uncomfortable relationship and how
important it is to allow in high
variance individuals into a world which
now attempts to shut them out by
claiming that we need excellence at all
costs and highly agreeable people with
very small variants this is a one-way
ticket to irrelevance see nature
provides a lot of very difficult people
who are very disagreeable with very high
variances particularly the learning
disabled community has very high
variances and I believe that they're not
eliminated to eliminate it from the gene
pool for a reason I believe that they're
there to be the innovators and so we're
killing our own innovative class with
all of these extra requirements for
collegiality or diversity or
some kind of regularity because often
everybody on the team has one idea and
the idea that you need is that one guy
who won't go along so how do we get
people who are if you know the Asch
conformity experiment ash- that is that
they don't go along with what everybody
is pretending to claim as their own
perspective on each card there are
several lines your task is a very simple
one you're to look at the line on the
left and determine which of the three
lines on the right is equal to it in
length two to two to the subject denies
the evidence of his own eyes and yields
to group influence we also want people
who are Milgram negative if you know the
Milgram experiment Stanley Milgram if
you make an error however you'll be
punished with an electric shock so of
course it is to your advantage that you
learn all these word pairs as quickly as
possible
completely you want people who when
asked to push the bus buzzer to
administer an electric shock tell the
experimenter to buzz off rather than the
people who go along with it when they're
assured that they will not be held
personally responsible so in part you
have to recognize that heroic behavior
comes from a group of people who in
general are viewed as somewhat unsavory
by the mainstream and that's fine what
makes you so certain that those kind of
individuals are not part of the
establishment at the moment well first
of all even where they are part of the
establishment at the moment they talk to
us in hushed tones like oh you don't
know how it got how bad it's gotten I
can't say that anymore
fifteen years ago I could say that now I
could lose my job like you're actually
those people are still there but they're
not free to think and the penalty for
like a single misstep me even though the
maginot have a bad thought you say a bad
thing was at the end of your career
we're gonna dispose of high ability
people because they may told an
off-colored joke and the wrong
setting like that's insane I don't know
how to have a say it like you could have
somebody who might be on the verge of a
cure for cancer and if they told some
joke that offended somebody's gender
sensibilities that person could be out
of a job well that's insane and it's
very important to understand that level
of intolerance of fragility has to be
driven out of the institutions that
require these high agency individuals
and is your sense that that process of
excellence keeping out genius is
actually a civilizational threat or is
is partly to do with the the situation
that we find ourselves in yeah I mean
let's just let's just talk about
disagree ability as a trait right now we
have all sorts of things that need
people to say no to them and to point
the way towards something else no we
should not be pushing for citizenship
for everyone in the in the country who's
here illegally no we should not be
allowing the claim that Islam is the
religion of peace and therefore the
least close to any kind of violent act
obviously they've got a problem and we
they need our help and we need their
help we need to be talking about these
things obviously trade is extremely
redistributed and to claim that it makes
that it makes a rising tide which raises
all boats is malpractice for an
economist to mouth those words we need
to clean house for people who are lying
obviously lying about very simple things
and the only people who are likely to be
those the people are going to say that
are going to be people with their own
theories they're going to be people who
are highly disagreeable highly creative
and somewhat self-destructive we want
those people rather than the egg we have
excellent people and that's our problem
it's a plague and it's not that
excellence is bad
that we have way too many excellent
people in proportion to the numbers of
geniuses and heroes in the population
Sewell Wright is an evolutionary
biologist and a beautiful and analogy of
this called a fitness landscape and his
perspective was when you're doing things
mostly right you can figure out how to
do them a little bit better by figuring
out what gets you a slightly better
outcome with small variations so this
was analogized to climbing a little hill
of fitness but if you imagine that
fundamentally you're pretty close to the
top and the really high fitness peak is
across a valley that you have to go down
to go up what does that feel like in
terms of an innovator how does an
innovator experience well you might see
yourself maxing out your credit cards
you might see your relationship in
tatters you might see that you've
over-promised and under-delivered and
you've got only two weeks to come up
with a solution and you've got nothing
the kinds of people who are willing to
take on those sorts of assignments are
going to be very frightening to the
general population and great that's
wonderful we have to make sure that
those people have a home in science in
startups in journalism and sense-making
and anything innovative so that
fundamentally you don't get these levels
of consensus around total nonsense that
keep cropping up inside of the
institutional framework
I think what they do is they construct
very durable narratives about people who
refuse to go along
so in general when I hear the word
consensus my initial hit on the word
consensus is negative why is that it's
because if everybody agrees that
something is true like two plus three
equals five you don't need a consensus
nobody talks about the arithmetic
consensus everybody who doesn't
subscribe to the arithmetic consensus
goes nowhere they can't build a house
they can they can't you know I handle
money okay so there is no need to call
it the earth metic consensus on the
other hand if things are actually
open-ended very rare for people to all
bunched together around one set of
tentative ideas so what you find is that
in general you would expect a cacophony
of people each with their own pet ideas
when things are genuinely uncertain or
you would find everybody falling in line
when more or less it's clear that that
the world goes one particular way so in
general I think what's going on with the
consensus is that a consensus is usually
achieved through some sort of
incentivizing people as the as the mobs
the violent mobs in Mexico say Plateau
or Plomo do you want silver or do you
want lead so you're given a certain
amount of encouragement to come to a
particular perspective maybe in terms of
grant money or speaking opportunities
and you're given a disincentive which is
this is what's going to happen to your
career if you don't fall in line and so
using a plateau up low mo model you
suddenly get a lot of people pretending
that they all agree to some kind of
consensus position consensus thinking
almost destroyed the financial system in
2008 Eric had been warning about the
danger of mortgage-backed securities
since 2002 I got very involved in
economics tried to bring some of the
discipline
came from theoretical physics and
differential geometry into neoclassical
economic theory or some of the first
people to become alarmed about the role
of mortgage-backed securities and their
ability to potentially blow up the world
economic system by 2008 it had become
clear to everyone that we built a
massive society wide fiction which the
mandarins had called the Great
Moderation
and this is one of the things that gives
me confidence that when large numbers of
well credentialed and well-spoken
experts sitting in the most powerful
positions in your society all agree on
something you should not be intimidated
or cow because what's quite possible is
that groupthink has taken over the
entire system and after 2009 when we
held a conference at the Perimeter
Institute where we tried to bring in
people from outside the financial
community to look at the financial
crisis
welcome to the economic Manhattan
Project I got a very good view of why
and how the individual expert
communities resist visitors from other
fields because the visitors from other
fields don't have any allegiances and
the people who are in that particular
field have built up to very defensive
positions so I I got a chance to see
well what happens when you bring
mathematicians computer scientists
theoretical physicists corporate
executives to look at the financial
crisis the guys who are actually doing
finance get very freaked out and they
circle the wagons
people sense that there's something
about the incentive structures that
makes the conclusions untrustworthy even
when the conclusions are right and
sometimes the conclusions of the
consensus are right that's not the issue
I think climate is a situation which my
guess is is that the climate consensus
is probably correct in some sense but
many of us are very disturbed by our
ability to see incentives pushing people
to hold certain conclusions so I think I
think that that structure is enforced by
taking anyone who's outside of the
consensus and attaching concepts to
their name so one of the experiments I
tried was controversial professor Paul
Krugman versus controversial professor
or Jordan Peterson Paul Krugman has been
a controversial professor professor for
decades but there wasn't a single hit on
all of Google for the phrase
controversial professor Paul Krugman
because this is one of the tricks inside
of what I called the gut gated
institutional narrative or the Jin so in
the Jin the way it works is that you
have these set phrases could be you know
controversial strong man Bashar al-asad
okay well what is that telling us it's
the news media opining that we should be
picking aside and that he should be on
the opposite side so when you have a
situation where the news media wants to
promote somebody like Paul Krugman they
don't call him controversial professor
Paul Krugman they call him New York
Times columnist or Nobel laureate Paul
Krugman but if it's Jordan Peterson and
Jordan hasn't signed up for some sort of
consensus position he has to be
controversial professor Jordan Peterson
now it's true that he's a controversial
professor but that's actually the gated
institutional narrative special language
for telling the audience who the good
guys and the bad guys are and if you go
back to professional wrestling this
would be called heels and baby faces or
faces and so the idea is that Paul
Krugman would be a face and Jordan
Peterson
be a heel but instead of being open
about the fact that wrestling is a
simulated performance sport in the
journalistic endeavor we pretend the
journalism is actually a search for
truth which I find hysterically
and you've described this as kayfabe in
the past rightfully can you explain what
that is to people who'd maybe not heard
that sure I think one of the problems is
that we don't have good language for
dealing with multi-layered deception and
the two places that I thought had pretty
good language with the intelligence
community and professional wrestling so
professional wrestling was the easier
it's hard to get spooks to give up their
secrets so what I did is I started to
look into professional wrestling and
what is order all of the terms that they
have to maintain to keep track what the
actual storylines are with the simulated
storyline sometimes you have a simulated
storyline that apparently breaks into
actual reality or like you're breaking
the fourth wall but it's actually a
controlled structure where you're still
in a fake story so they call things that
are fake works and they call things that
are real shoots so a a worked shoot is
actually something that is set inside of
a fake storyline is apparently real and
breaks the fourth wall but is in fact
fake so you're talking about tertiary
and eventually quaternary levels of
deception I don't think the human mind
can do much more than four layers of
life but kayfabe is the organized
structure of lies that undergirds
professional wrestling and is kept it as
a simulated sport for about a century
all sorts of human activity vir between
utter terror and boredom and why is that
well because if something is actually an
unbounded negative potential experience
people are very hesitant to engage so if
two wrestlers can really do damage to
each other they're gonna circle each
other for a very long time before
engaging because they don't want to risk
anything that they don't have to so you
could have bouts that would go on for
four or five hours and basically nothing
happened well this is true in all sorts
of endeavors people in the know and
finance don't really want to risk their
money so they come up with all sorts of
elaborate ways to make sure that they're
going
to be okay no matter what happens in
politics the same is true nobody wants
to simply find that they're out of a job
because they lost an election so there's
an elaborate revolving door between
politically related occupations like
punditry
or lobbying and actually being a
representative so you have all sorts of
fakery that is entitled that is intended
rather to make stable careers for the
participants and to present an engaging
and regular product for those in the
audience and so I believe that in some
sense what you're seeing is what I call
K fabrication where real activities that
are dangerous and or boring tend to get
sanitized by the participants so that
they can present and as if product to
those outside of the structure and not
themselves get hurt and continue to make
money off of it and I think that that's
what happened in professional wrestling
there's a real competition for airtime
for for fame but there's a fake
competition which is a scripted series
of pretend bouts where the decisions are
actually known in advance and that's
very similar to what I see happening in
war and Finance in media and
particularly journalism I think you've
spoken before about the sense that these
systems get weaker and weaker as they
continue why do you think that is which
systems well the political system for
example that it seems that as time has
gone on the choices that we're being
given in the political system get weaker
and weaker well because you're driving
you're systematically driving out the
people who should be trying to lead
you're making it so unpleasant to hold
real opinions to have real integrity
you're driving the costs of the specific
group of people we need so that instead
the only people who are going to show up
are the people that we should fear
there's the New York Times article that
came out and kind of named the IDW is
there a kind of paradox in it's no
longer dark what was never dark and that
was a large part of the joke
we have only been dark to one thing and
that thing is the institutional media
and the main platforms be they academic
or governmental so if you will I think
that the mainstream media has pretended
not to notice us as just as they
pretended to find it everything we say
either vapid or outrageous but I think
that you know with what's really going
on is that there's been a monopoly
effectively on narrative held by the
collection of major institutional voices
the true spectrum of thought is far
broader than people have been led to
believe and I think that's where the IDW
comes in that we are it's not that we're
just outside of the Overton Window many
of the points we're making really aren't
found anywhere inside of mainstream
media and established institutions even
though many of these things that we are
talking about are simply commonplace
observations did you have any doubts
about about New York Times article I
mean I had I had an infinite number of
doubts about the New York Times article
part of me wants to work quietly and
part of me realizes that we have to work
in some public facing capacity and I
personally have found it much more
comfortable to have a private life to
not have everything that I'm thinking
broadcast to a large audience but I
think we've run out of time and so I
think some of us are somewhat
reluctantly choosing to make a different
call now so you're talking about a
different way of thinking people who
have a different way of thinking is that
what characterizes the members of the
IDW it's hard to say I mean I would say
that everybody in the IDW is fairly
disagreeable in the
the Big Five personality inventory so
can you hold a position when you're the
only person in a room that believes that
thing like if it's you versus a hundred
people I would say almost everybody in
the core of the IDW is capable of
holding a position where everyone is
against you and I think that that trait
is extremely rare
do you see the IDW is primarily a
political project no I don't I see it
primarily as a precursor to anything
decent it's what has to succeed for us
to have a political conversation I don't
think we're having a political
conversation either internationally or
nationally I think we have people who
are talking about nonsense positions we
just went back to the immigration
position there are only two positions
I'm convinced aren't political one is
open borders which is never going to
happen and the other one is closed
borders which is never going to happen
and yet you very often encounter people
who are talking in these terms as if
these are the actual positions so I
don't think that we're having a
political conversation I think that
what's been going on is is that the
mainstream media has been playing
keep-away ball right so this game where
you're throwing the ball over somebody
who's trying to catch it now the public
has been trying to get in on this
conversation but what keeps happening is
is that our fake left and our fake right
are engaged in a completely fake
conversation about fake items including
fake news which they themselves are
pushing out and then claiming to fight
fake news so the whole thing is so
saturated in falsehood that people are
waking up to the idea
oh I forgotten what it sound sounded
like for people to actually have a
discussion about a topic and how much
time it takes you know in general it
can't be done with four or five voices
on a panel in 10 minutes with a few
commercial interruptions they're just
almost nothing can be discussed that way
and what's what's worse is that the very
people who would be best able to discuss
it are never going to be invited on to
those programs in a way the people in
the IDW have been selected for like a
lot of them have had quite high-profile
encounters you look at
Sam Harris with Ben Affleck or you look
at Brett Weinstein and there's a sense
that they've in some way had to live out
their ideas there's a sense of bravery
that they've had to stick up for
themselves
Jordan Peterson and C 16 I mean you
could you can list a lot of times where
as you said they had to be that one
person who was thinking a certain thing
no I mean I think I made the point
probably on the Rubin report that what's
going on is that when you ask any large
collection of people to salute a
nonsensical flag and pledge allegiance
to it and more or less everyone makes
the calculation
I guess if this is going to get me
through my day I'll salute any flag then
you've got the one gal or one guy who
doesn't want to well my observation is
that that person is usually sitting on
an entire mountain of interesting
thoughts that they don't have the
freedom to simply make a convenience
readjustment and so from that
perspective yeah in general if you ask a
thousand people to salute a flag that
makes no sense and tell them that
they'll be incentivize you'll get a
thousand-dollar check at the end or you
know you won't lose your job and
somebody stands up and says no way I'm
getting out of here
do what you want that person is usually
much more interesting than just being a
contrarian that person is usually saying
no because they've got an entire
worldview that is built by hand and and
bespoke and so that's why this method of
finding people has been relatively
fruitful it's people who don't back down
usually don't back down for a reason
because there's every reason just to go
along it seems that the the phenomena of
the IDW is is part of this great
intellectual awakening I mean you're
seeing people being really hungry for
long-form content on YouTube 3-hour
conversations people are are clearly
hungry for a lot more intellectual
stimulation they don't actually agree
with this I mean this is an idea that I
think Jordan has slightly wrong so for a
while I've been making the point that
there was a change between
writing for television was sort of the
lowest form of of an art and that
writing for movies allowed for real
character development but that the multi
season multi episode shows with very
long storylines actually has the
greatest character development and so
that the greatest writers are now
writing for TV the important thing to
understand is is that it's not just the
advent of long-form podcasting what it
is is having the courage to say
something using that medium you have
long-form podcasts that aren't
attracting almost anybody and the only
reason that the IDW is behaving in a
different fashion is that it's Merritt
marrying the content that brave people
are starved for with the change in
technology and so in general most things
don't work in a three-hour format what
works in a three-hour format is when
you're living through what I'm calling
left par theism where the modern left
which is my side of the aisle has gone
so completely insane that people are
starved for normal conversation as if it
was some is that in the former Soviet
Union and so you have an underground
network if you will that is supplying
that need for reality and the only
reason we're underground is because the
mainstream is pretending for the most
part not to notice that this phenomenon
is existing which is fascinating and
you've described this as a civil war
within the left could you could you
explain what you mean by that sure the
left that I relate to is the left that
realizes that the past cannot supply the
answers and that we have to actually
progress because we can't stay here it
is not the left that believes we can
wish ourselves into a beautiful future
by pretending that the Reap that the
world is different than it actually is
so I think that the key thing that it is
an agreement between these two groups is
that we have to get to some sort of
better place and that is that the
progressive in progressivism where we
are deeply divided and you know again
these are the divisions that are is much
worse than between left and right how
these absolutely imbecilic figures
believe that you can just wish yourself
into paradise that you don't have to
worry about markets that you can just
say you know free good things for
everybody well it just doesn't make a
whit of sense or you know you're going
to wish human beings to be both
simultaneously non-diverse so that you
can argue that any difference in
pro-rata shares of a group in any
occupation is evidence of oppression and
then you're going to turn around and
argue that people are actually
incredibly different because we're gonna
get a huge benefit from diversity I mean
this is not even self consistent this is
this would be offensive to an
intelligent five-year-old so I don't
really believe that these progressives
as they call themselves and regressives
as some of us call them are even making
serious intellectual points they're sort
of trolling by pretending to believe in
all things that just gum up the works
and so it's very important to me that
not only do we not really spend time
debating people who are not serious in
their intellectualism but that we
realize that it is important to the
diversity of mature and important ideas
that we not spend undue effort engaging
ideas that are functioning very
differently from regular conversation it
is as if somebody asks should we have a
diverse dinner tonight well we could
invite somebody from this position from
that country from this gender and then
should we should we invite a suicide
bomber well if you're a suicide bomber
you're that bit of diversity is going to
take down the entire conversation
as well as all the people at the table
right well these are like suicide
bombers in terms of their ideas they are
attaching themselves to real
conversations and blowing up the
conversation so that you can't actually
speak and I think what we need is we
need to realize that the diversity of
ideas that have to be explored hinges
are not allowing in bad diversity that
is you don't want a single person at the
table who wants to scuttle the
conversation and that's not something
that we've understood about the modern
left the modern left is very often
focused on scuttling any realistic
conversation so that it can continue to
threaten and terrorize people into
pretending to hold positions that no
sane person could possibly hold why do
you think it's become like this well I
think my wife probably has the best
explanation which is that when you're
actually dependent on labor for your
voter base labor has economic issues so
this is the great search for something
cheaper than labor and identity turns
out to be much cheaper than labor if you
can get somebody to vote for you where
you're gonna take their future their
security and their retirement but you're
going to celebrate the fact you know
that they came from Laos that's a bad
deal nothing against the Laotians but
for God's sakes stand up for yourself as
a worker before you you know stand up
for yourself as somebody who needs to
see Southeast Asia celebrated on the
national stage it's not that exciting
demand more from from your
representatives this is the great search
for the cheapest possible constituency
and that's exactly why I think it's
happening I think it's because the
traditional Democratic voter base was
too expensive they wanted real change
they wanted to participate economically
they wanted to participate at the level
of power and the the donor base said is
there isn't there anything cheaper than
labor and
they found something and where do you
hope that this IDW conversation will go
in the future well I hope it goes to the
heart of everything that is denying our
ability to use our eyes on our ears and
our minds as decent people if you're
simply observing the world as it is and
you're thinking about it with a big open
heart and you're trying to be decent
about it at the same time that you're
trying to provide for your family
and concerned about your country's
welfare there's no reason that you
should be huddling in the cupboard
afraid that if anyone hears that you
think that men are different from women
that you're going to be consigned to the
dustbin of history and fired for it it's
really essential that people stop being
terrorized for holding garden-variety
positions
[Music]
you